A Guide to the Accomack County (Va.) Records, 1697-1947 circa, undated
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Accomack County (Va.) Records, 1697-1947 circa, undated
The Library of Virginia
1048660, 1122002, 1122030, 1122035, 1122037, 1176534, 1200398, 1204975, 1208486, 1208593
10 boxes
Accomack County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court records from Accomack County. Barcode number 1200398 was transferred under accession number 44262.
Historical Information
Accomack County was named for the Accomac Indians, who lived on the Eastern Shore at the time of the first English settlement in Virginia. The word means "on-the-other-side-of-water place" or "across the water." It was one of the original eight shires, or counties, first enumerated in 1634 and spelled Accomac without the k. The county's name was changed to Northampton County in 1643. The present county was formed from Northampton about 1663. In October 1670, the General Assembly temporarily reunited Accomack and Northampton Counties as Northampton County. In November 1673, Accomack County was again separated from Northampton. In early records, the county's name was spelled many ways. In 1940 the General Assembly adopted the present spelling, Accomack. The county gained a small part of the southern end of Smith's Island from Somerset County, Maryland, in 1879, after the United States had approved boundary changes between Virginia and Maryland that had been agreed to in 1877. The county seat is Accomac.
Scope and Content
Accomack County (Va.) Records, 1697-1947 circa, consist of the following records series: Road and Bridge Records; Bonds, Commissions, Oaths; Tax and Fiscal Records; Military and Pension Records; Fiduciary Records; Clerks' Records; Election Records; Board of Supervisors Records; Overseers of the Poor Records; School Records; Marriage Records and Vital Statistics Miscellaneous Records; Court Records; Land Records; Wills; Commissioner of the Revenue Records; and Township Records.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Accomack County Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm" found on the Library of Virginia's web site.
Accomack County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Accomack County Records may be found in the Virginia Lost Records Localities Collection at the Library of Virginia. Search the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection available at Virginia Memory.
For more information and a listing of lost records localities see Lost Records research note.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Accomack County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records--Virginia-- Accomack County.
Geographical Names:
Accomack County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia-- Accomack County.
Contents List
- Records, 1735-1850 circa
  Road and Bridge Records; Bonds/Commissions/Oaths; Tax and Fiscal Records; Military and Pension Records; Fiduciary Records
- Records, 1720-1940 circa
  Tax and Fiscal Records; Court Records: Clerks' Records; Election Records; Board of Supervisors Records; Overseers of the Poor Records; School Records; Bonds/Commissions/Oaths
- Records, 1785-1947 circa
  Tax and Fiscal Records; Board of Supervisors Records; Election Records: Copies of property tax books for commissioners of elections, 1846-1849, Abstracts of votes, undated; Marriage Records and Vital Statistics: Death registers, 1868, 1870-1871, 1873; Miscellaneous Records: Register of sloop "Little Betsey", 1785
- Records, 1720-1800 ca.
  Court Records: Judgments, etc.; Land Records: Deeds, dower papers, etc.; Wills; Fiduciary Records: Inventories, appraisements, etc. Documents are extremely fragile.
- Records, 1775-1891 circa
  School Records: Promotional material - Commercial College of Kentucky University, 1891; Military and Pension Records: Militia appointment, 1775; Miscellaneous Records: United States Telegraph 1834 November 4
- Records, 1700-1920 circa
  Road and Bridge Records, Bonds/Commissions/Oaths, Tax and Fiscal Records, etc. (unprocessed)
- Records, 1845-1910
  Election Records: Lists of voters, 1865-1866; Tax and Fiscal Records: Copies of land books by parish, 1845; Commissioner of the Revenue Records, 1851, 1910; Board of Supervisors Records, 1876; Township Records: Pungoteague Township accounts, 1874 circa; Miscellaneous Records: Captain Southey Millener accounts, 1851 circa,
- Records, 1725-1786
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Oaths of Allegiance, 1757-1758; Justice of the Peace Appointments, 1761-1762; Commission of Peace, 1745, 1777; Oyer and Terminer Commissions and Test Oath, 1740-1777; Miscellaneous Records: Census of Tobacco Plants, 1725, 1728-1729; Tax and Fiscal Records: Tithable Lists, 1728-1769 and undated; Tax list related to Revolutionary War debt, 1786 circa
- Records, 1727-1807
  Fiduciary Records: Executor and Administrator Bonds Book, 1727-1728, Executor Bonds Book, 1771, 1777, 1780; Orphans Bond Books, 1766, 1788-1790; Court Records: Clerks' Finance Records: Fee Book, 1807,
- Records, 1697-1836
  Court Records: Judgments, 1740, 1752, 1785; List of Actions, 1722-1723; Minute Book page, 1722; Fiduciary Records, 1697, 1786; Land Records, 1774; Miscellaneous Records: Request for wool, 1836; Overseers of the Poor Records, 1779, 1788-1789; Tax and Fiscal Records, 1782, 1809.